<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rodrigo Farinha</title>
    <description>Rodrigo Farinha</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 21:19:45 -0300</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2025 21:19:45 -0300</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.3.4</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Welcome</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-im-starting-this-blog&quot;&gt;Why I’m Starting This Blog&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been thinking about having a personal blog for a long time. I always told myself I’d start “later”—when life was less hectic or when my ideas felt more solid. But “later” never came. And still, the urge to share thoughts kept coming back. So here we are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This first post is a simple note to myself (and to anyone else reading) about why this blog exists—and maybe just as importantly, why it doesn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-this-blog-isnt&quot;&gt;What This Blog &lt;em&gt;Isn’t&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many reasons I’m starting this blog, but before getting into them, I think it’s helpful to be clear about what I’m &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; trying to do here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I’m not chasing an audience.&lt;/strong&gt; I’m not trying to grow a following or optimize for clicks and keywords. If that were the goal, I’d probably be better off using Substack.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I’m not picking a single topic.&lt;/strong&gt; My interests jump around—from strategy to AI, tech, books, and whatever else is on my mind.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I’m not setting a strict schedule.&lt;/strong&gt; Some months I might write a lot; others, nothing at all—and I’m okay with that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-why-write&quot;&gt;So Why Write?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what’s pushing me to hit “publish”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To think out loud.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Writing helps me organize and question my own ideas. Sharing them adds a little pressure to make sense.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To improve how I write.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
You don’t learn to write by waiting for perfect sentences; you learn by writing imperfect ones, publicly squirming, then doing it again.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To keep track of what I care about.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This blog is a public memory of things I found interesting or important at the time I wrote them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To open the door to new conversations.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Maybe someone reads a post, relates to it, and decides to get in touch. That alone makes it worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-you-might-find-here&quot;&gt;What You Might Find Here&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This won’t be a highly curated publication. Think of it more like a notebook I’ve left open on the table. Topics will probably include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Artificial intelligence&lt;/strong&gt; — ideas, tools, and things that break.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Business strategy&lt;/strong&gt; — especially where it connects with marketing, innovation, or behavior.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technology and tools&lt;/strong&gt; — scripts, apps, experiments that help me work or think better.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reading notes&lt;/strong&gt; — thoughts on books, papers, or articles that stuck with me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-comes-next&quot;&gt;What Comes Next&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know how often I’ll write or how polished things will be. But I’ll try to keep it honest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If something here sparks a thought—or a disagreement—feel free to reach out.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 14:06:00 -0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/welcome/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/welcome/</guid>
        
        
        <category>updates</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
